Guide to the Records of the Andiron Club of New York City MC.19
New York University Archives
Records of the Andiron Club of New York City
1907-1982
1907-1943
New York University Archives
Andiron Club of New York City
MC.19
19.5 Linear Feet in 32 boxes and 1 flat box
The collection documents the operation of the Andiron Club of New York City since its founding in 1907. It includes correspondence with members and visiting speakers; minutes of Council and general meetings; curricula vitae and lists of the membership; financial records; photographs; publications; and reprints.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The New York University Archives acquired the Andiron Club records in several installments. Professor James Tuttleton made the first donation (1979) of 5 linear inches, which consisted of club newsletters and photographs. Then, on June 22, 1983, he donated twenty-eight volumes (58") to the Fales Library. Soon afterwards, Fales transferred the materials to the NYU Archives. The materials were donated by Prof. James Tuttleton on behalf of the club council. The transfer from Fales was made by Patricia McGuire, assistant curator. The approximate dates of the materials range from 1907-1943. The second installment came in December 1984 directly from the club to the Archives. Prof. John Maynard donated a few pages of notes documenting the people with whom he had correspondence during his term. Joan Pyser, president in 1985, also donated her correspondence, as well as one linear inch of the correspondence of other dictators (mostly of Michael Shugrue). In October of 1984 it was decided that these materials should forever remain in the Archives. Shortly thereafter additional material was donated by Joan Pyser and James Tuttleton on behalf of the club; another 22" was donated directly to the Archives. These materials consisted of correspondence (1939-1943), the scrapbook of Congressman Steven B. Ayers (1912-1918), club ledgers, reprinted pamphlets, a set of the "Colonnade," and other printed materials. The accession number associated with this collection is 85.048.
Arrangement
Folders are generally arranged chronologically in seven series:
Correspondence
Minutes
Vitae
Ledgers
Photographs
Congressman Steven B. Ayers
Printed Materials and Publications
Historical Note
On December 20th, 1907, a group of college instructors and undergraduates met before an open fire and planned two institutions: the Andiron Club and the Colonnade. They came together with the purpose of proliferating the old European philosophical assemblies where learning and erudition mixed with good fellowship. Such a club was in keeping with all the values associated with the belle époque of the 19th century. It seems as if the club operated with one mind, one final cause as it were, but in reality there were several dedicated young men who constituted the core of the group for several years. Among these individuals were M. G. Bishop, John W. Draper, George B. Hotchkiss, Arthur H. Nason, S. M. Tucker, and Henry Melville Love. These men exemplified the role of scholar and friend through the early days of the club, establishing an Andiron tradition, which has kept this club alive up to the present day (1988). In the early days, club rules and goals were well defined. A 1914 statement of policy (see Club Manual) affirmed the tradition of "Romantic Idealism over Naturalism and Realism," and proceeded to publish accordingly, in The Colonnade (1907 to 1922), pieces most appropriate to their doctrine.
In the days before the war and before faculty constituted the majority of members, the club flaunted a youthful fraternity-like atmosphere. Some of the rules of the Club were as follows:
No.3: That the Andiron Club strive to keep its roll of members free from the name of any man not literary in his sympathies and an enthusiastic supporter of literary work.
No.11: Have no relations save the most casual and informal kind with the downtown schools.
No.12: Let the fraudulent contributor be ostracized.
No.15: Maintain an enticing secrecy about the affairs of the Andiron Club.
No.17: Have nothing to do with the Eucleian. (The Eucleian Society was a rival student literary society established in the early nineteenth century at New York University.)
The early history of the Andiron Club falls roughly into four distinct periods: (1) the years between its birth in 1907 to the beginning of the Draper administration, 1913-17; (2) 1925-26, with the interregnum, during World War I, of Carey C.D. Briggs; (3) the dictatorship of Royal J. Davis, from 1926 to 1934; and (4) Frederick S. Boas, Professor of English at Columbia University, who became the dictator following the death of Davis.
The Bronx University Heights campus was all-male and as a consequence, Andiron was not open to women until 1968. Original members frequently donned tuxedos and puffed on cigars during meetings, but institutional chauvinism gradually died. In the 1950s Andiron rapidly lost its members and membership was principally elderly alumni, and although excellent speakers occasionally appeared, the club was on the verge of collapse. Then, Coleman Parsons, a professor of English with no affiliation with NYU, was named dictator. He enthusiastically extended membership so that it included any studious man or woman, regardless of professional status or educational background. He used his academic connections to insure programs of consequence and once again literary scholars of note tried out their theories on an active body of perceptive generalists.
Dr. Parsons' four years as dictator (now called "president") was followed by a succession of distinguished men and the club's first woman president: Edmond Volpe, now President of the College of Staten Island; Arthur Waldhorn, first and third Director of the Davis Center of the Performing Arts; James Tuttleton, Chairman of English at New York University; Frederick Goldin; John Maynard, Chairman of English at New York University; and Michael Joan Peyser, President of the Andiron Club of New York City.
These dictators who succeeded Coleman Parsons, although they continued to emphasize the literary and scholarly traditions of Andiron, extended its scope. In addition to literary scholars and biographer-scholars, such as Martin Duberman, Leon Edel, Robert Gutman, Edgar Johnson, Aileen Ward, we heard working critics such as Leslie Fiedler, Helen Vendler, Denis Donoghue, Pauline Kael, John Simon, and Diana Trilling; and novelists such as Joseph Heller, Anthony Burgess, Malcom Bosse, E. L. Doctorow, and Toni Morrison; art historians, Sir John Pope-Hennessy and Robert Rosenblum; poets, John Hollander and Galway Kinnell; musicians and musicologists who included Charles Rosen, Sir Rudolf Bing, Steven Sondheim, Judith Raskin and Alan Rich; cultural historians including Paul Fussell and Joseph Murphy, Chancellor of the University.
Related Materials
Records of the Eucleian Society (RG 39.1)
Records of the Philomathean Society (RG 39.2)
Scope and Contents
The collection is very complete from 1907 to 1943, but afterwards sporadic. Still, much less material was generated after the 1940s, so, in that context, we cannot be sure of the magnitude of outstanding material. It is fairly certain that the Andiron private library (the titles of which may be found in the club bibliography and club manual) has been broken up over the years.
The production of "The Colonnade," or any facsimile thereof, ended in 1922. The complete set of "Colonnades" are bound and housed in this collection.
These records and publications of the Andiron Club extend themselves to diverse areas of academic pursuit. Apart from the obvious biographical and literary value of the records, one might investigate socioeconomic issues and the management of a literary club using these records.
In brief, the collection contains a literary journal, club newsletters, annals, minutes, council minutes, scrapbooks, memorabilia, photographs, ledgers, notices, correspondence, some original manuscripts and other writings, a book by Prof. Nason and a book by Prof. Draper, membership lists, address books, lecture notes, and transcripts of speeches.
Memorabilia.; Correspondence.; Newsletters.; Literature -- Societies, etc.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches.; Minutes (administrative records); Membership lists.; Ledgers (account books); Announcements.; Manuscripts; Journals (periodicals); Photographs.; Student activities.; Address books; Books.; annals (histories, without comment); Lecture notes.; Volpe, Edmond Loris; Waldhorn, Arthur, 1918-; Ayres, Steven B. (Steven Beckwith), 1861-1929; Andiron Club of New York City; Draper, John William, 1893-; Davis, Royal Jenkins, 1878-; Peyser, Michael; New York University -- Societies, etc.; Tuttleton, James W.; Tucker, S. Marion (Samuel Marion), 1876-1962; Goldin, Frederick; Frederick, S. (Frederick Samuel); Nason, Arthur Huntington, 1877-1944; Hotchkiss, George Burton, 1884-1953
- Series I: Correspondence, 1936-1982
  Scope and Contents
  The first series contains correspondence from 1936 to 1982. The series contains letters from club dictators and outside scholars. Letters generally pertain to club business rather than literary topics.
  - Correspondence, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Barcode #: 3 1142 042258296
  - Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225829 6
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, circa 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225830 4
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1953 (Box 30)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1959 (Box 31)
  - Correspondence, 1923-1965 (Box 32)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1971 (Box 33)
- Series II: Minutes, 1907-1971
  "Minutes" correspond to "Annals," "General Minutes," "Council Minutes," "Club Manual," and "The Book of the Poker."
  The Annals (1907-12) were an early version of the general minutes and contain treasury reports, a 1912 statement of policy, minutes of the meetings, etc. The Annals also contain a poem sent to the club by "The New Yorker" (an NYU literary club), which pokes fun at the Andiron journal's ("Colonnade") obfuscations of the founding fathers. Judging from the dates, this volume represents the first volume of the general minutes which hereafter begin "Volume II, Volume III etc..." (See Box 3)
  The General Minutes, 1912-43 are volumes containing meticulous records of club meetings: what was discussed, news about members, treasury reports (although the Council Minutes would be the best place to investigate financial matters), news about poetry readings, recitals, lectures, summations of lectures and rebuttals, announcements concerning dinners (such as "Ladies' Night"), annual events, reunions, letters from members and non-members from abroad; and general club business such as the creation of new rules, the voting in of new members, credentials of potential members, and the bestowal of membership upon professors of foreign Universities. (Boxes l, 5-10)
  The Council Minutes 1926-43 contains membership tables and comparative financial statements. Of special interest, the last page of volume IV contains a page-long reference to the War Powers Act of 1938 and its subsequent interpretation by the club. (Boxes 3-4)
  The Club Manual 1914 contains the club constitution, by-laws, club roster, and a statement of purpose (i.e. to publish the "Colonnade" and to affirm Romantic Idealism). Also there are two lists of Andiron Club members, plus a list of club publications (that is, articles published by club members). This kind of list is crucial for a researcher trying to trace literary sentiments. (Box 10)
  The Book of the Poker 1913 is a handwritten document (probably written by Henry Melville Love) that, in part, notes attitudes of members toward each other and toward literary criticism in general. Written in high prose and verse by the mysterious "Poker," it underpins the intimacy of the Andiron Club. Among other things, the "Poker" contains a defense of Romantic Idealism, while refusing to acknowledge the so-called "decadent" art movement as valid or pure. (Box 10)
  The club Bibliography 1907-40 lists some of the publications of its members. (Box 10)
  - Annals, 1907-1912 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225831 2
  - Minutes, 1926-1933 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1933-1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225832 0
  - Minutes, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1941-1948 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1912-1914 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1914-1923 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225833 8
  - Minutes, 1924-1928 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1928-1930 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225834 6
  - Minutes, 1930-1932 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225835 3
  - Minutes, 1932-1933 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1933-1935 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225836 1
  - Minutes, 1935-1937 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1937-1939 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225837 9
  - Minutes, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1940-1941 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1941-1944 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225838 7
  - Minutes, 1942-1943 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Club Manual, 1914 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Book of the Poker, 1914 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Club Bibliography, 1931-1934 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1942-1951 (Box 30)
  - Minutes, 1955-1959 (Box 31)
  - Minutes, 1953-1965 (Box 32)
  - Minutes, 1965-1971 (Box 33)
- Series III: Vitae, 1907-1941, 1960
  The vitae series contains the resumes of all members (whenever possible with updates over the years). Within that, extensive data on members: birthdays, marriage, current employers, publications, cross-references to Who's Who in America, and descriptions of military service. Updates of vitae were made in 1917, 1920, 1923, 1930, 1933, and 1943. The early members who may be found in Who's Who are as follows: M.G. Bishop, George B. Hotchkiss, Arthur H. Nason, S. M. Tucker, and Henry Melville Love. (Boxes 11-15)
  - Vitae, 1907-1923 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225839 5
  - Vitae, 1924-1930 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Vitae, 1930-1932 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225840 3
  - Vitae, 1933-1936 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225841 1
  - Vitae, 1937-1939 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225842 9
  - Vitae, 1939-1940 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225843 7
  - Vitae (unbound), 1941 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Vitae (unbound), 1960 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Ledgers, 1931-1941
  These four large ledgers record all monetary transactions from 1931 to 1941. (Box 16)
  - Ledgers, 1931-1936 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225844 5
  - Ledgers, 1931-1937 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Ledgers, 1932-1935 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Ledgers, 1936-1941 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Series V: Photographs, 1907-1982, undated
  The majority of the photographs are portraits of Andiron Club members dating between 1907 and 1982.
  - Photographs, 1907-1982, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225845 2
  - Photographs, 1907-1982, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1907-1982, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Series VI: Congressman Steven B. Ayres, 1910-1922
  Contains primarily articles about the Congressman, as well as some excerpts from scrapbooks. The materials generally refer to political matters which Congressman Steven B. Ayres acted upon.
  - Scrapbook, 1910-1914 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Steven B. Ayers: From the Scrapbook, 1910-1922 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225846 0
  - Steven B. Ayers: From the Scrapbook, 1913 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Steven B. Ayers: From the Scrapbook, 1914 (Box 19, Folder 3)
- Series VII: Printed Materials and Publications, 1907-circa 1980
  With the exception of 1935, the Newsletters are unbound and somewhat sporadic. Our last issue is in 1955 but we do not know when the last Newsletter was published. The years touched on by the Newsletter are: 1935, 1936, 1943, 1944, 1942, 1954, and 1955. The unbound Summons, each duplicated in the collection at least once, run from 1924 to 1932 (Boxes 20-22). The Publications and Reprints are of a miscellaneous nature in the way of pamphlets-bound and unbound books, programs (1910-1980). The pamphlets and re-prints run from 1910 to 1922, with a gap between 1916 and 1920 (Boxes 23-24). The "Colonnade," literary publication of the Andiron Club, is housed in this collection as well. The publication runs from 1907-1922. (Boxes 25-27)
  This collection also contains old programmes, two manuscripts written by club members, and a 1940 club directory.
  - Notices, 1931-1933 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225848 6
  - Notices, 1934-1937 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Summons, 1920-1923 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Summons/Newsletter, 1920-1923 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225849 4
  - Summons/Newsletter, 1923-1924 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Summons/Newsletter, 1923-1924 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Summons/Newsletter, 1924-1932 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Summons/Newsletter, 1924-1927 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225852 8
  - Summons/Newsletter, 1928-1931 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Summons/Newsletter, 1935-1955 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Summons/Newsletter, 1942-1943 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Bound Pamphlets and Reprints, 1910-1916 (Box 23, Folder 1, Box 34)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225851 0
  - Bound Pamphlets and Reprints, 1920-1921 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Bound Pamphlets and Reprints, 1922-1923 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Pamphlets, Reprints Unbound, circa 1920-1949 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225854 4
  - Harold's and Heraldry, A. Nason, 1907 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - The Hamlet of Shakespeare's Audience, W. Draper, 1939 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Programs, circa 1920, circa 1980 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1943, 1974 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - The Colonnade, 1908-1910 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225855 1
  - The Colonnade, 1910-1911 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - The Colonnade, 1911-1912 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - The Colonnade, 1912-1913 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - The Colonnade, 1913-1914 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - The Colonnade, 1914 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - The Colonnade, 1915 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225856 9
  - The Colonnade, 1915 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - The Colonnade, 1916 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - The Colonnade, 1919-1922 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225857 7
  - The Colonnade, 1919-1922 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - The Colonnade (Separates), 1911 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225858 5
  - The Colonnade (Separates), 1913 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - The Colonnade (Separates), 1914 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - The Colonnade (Separates), 1914 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - The Colonnade (Separates), 1915 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - The Colonnade (Separates), 1915 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225859 3
  - The Colonnade (Separates), 1916 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - The Colonnade (Separates), 1916 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - The Colonnade (Separates), 1917 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - The Colonnade (Separates), 1919 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Directory, 1940 (Box 30)
  - Newsletter, 1942-1945 (Box 31)
  - Earning Our Heritage Student Reports [Manuscript], n.d. (Box 31)
  - Newsletter, 1954-1955 (Box 32)
  - Old Programmes, 1954-1955 (Box 32)
  - A.H. Nason, "Toward My Obituary" [Manuscript], 1944 (Box 32)
  - Old programmes, 1939-1961 (Box 33)